<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and impartial account of Their Majesties army in Ireland Discovering the designs of the late K. James, and the French army, since the embarking and landing of His Grace the Duke of Schonberg, to this present time; with the particulars of what happened lately at the siege of Carickfergus, Dundalk, Charlemont, and Cavan, and of several other passages since the army went into winter quarters. Licensed March 28. 1690. J. Fraser.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2494A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220172</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831596</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63400)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2046:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and impartial account of Their Majesties army in Ireland Discovering the designs of the late K. James, and the French army, since the embarking and landing of His Grace the Duke of Schonberg, to this present time; with the particulars of what happened lately at the siege of Carickfergus, Dundalk, Charlemont, and Cavan, and of several other passages since the army went into winter quarters. Licensed March 28. 1690. J. Fraser.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for James Partridge at the Post-House at Charing-cross,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:36060:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A True and Impartial ACCOUNT of <hi>Their Majeſties Army in Ireland.</hi> Diſcovering the Deſigns of the Late K. <hi>JAMES,</hi> and the <hi>FRENCH</hi> ARMY, ſince the Embarking and Landing of His GRACE the DUKE of <hi>SCHONBERG,</hi> to this preſent Time; with the Particulars of what happened lately at the Siege of <hi>Carickfergus, Dundalk, Charlemont,</hi> and <hi>Cavan,</hi> and of ſeveral other Paſſages ſince the Army went into Winter Quarters.</head>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Licenſed <hi>March</hi> 28. 1690. <hi>J. Fraſer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>ON <hi>Monday</hi> the 21ſt. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1689. about Eight of the Clock in the Morning, his Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg,</hi> with fourteen Regiments of Foot, ſailed from <hi>High-lake,</hi> and ſafely landed at <hi>Banger,</hi> about One of the Clock in the Afternoon of the day following; upon the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Fleet, ſeveral ſmall Boats came from the Shoar, at leaſt two Leagues to meet it, to give an Account of the Country and the Harbours thereabouts, as alſo giving an Account of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, both Horſe, Dragoons, and Foot, flying from their Quarters upon the News of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army Landing. So great was the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation amongſt them, that ſeveral ran as far as <hi>Newry,</hi> being 36 Miles, before they ſtopt, to know either the quality or quantity of the Army. The appearance of our Fleet did ſo much comfort the Proteſtants of that Country, that the Shoar was covered with Horſes, Cows, and Sheep for the benefit and advantage of the Army, and Proviſions of all ſorts being ſo plentifully brought in; a quarter of good Mutton was ſold at four pence, and every thing elſe at very reaſonable rates. The General made Mr. <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Houſe at <hi>Banger</hi> his head Quarters, and giving Orders that all Men ſhould on pain of Death ſtand to Arms all that Night, having firſt very advantagiouſly lined ſome Hedges and Ditches with ſmall Shot. At Night an Allarm was in the Camp of the Enemies approach; whereupon the whole Army was reſolved to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Ground, but this afterwards appeared a Stratagem of War, to try the Mens courage in caſe the Enemy had really attackt them. The next day the General received Advice, that the Enemy then at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickfergus</hi> were intended to Plunder and Burn the Towns of <hi>Belfaſt</hi> and <hi>Lisburn;</hi> whereupon Collonel <hi>Wharton</hi>'s Regiment of Foot were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ordered to March from the Camp at <hi>Banger</hi> to <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> which was ſaved from Plunder and Fire, ſome of the Enemy being killed, and others taken Priſoners: Within two or three days afterwards, the Army decampt from <hi>Banger,</hi> and encampt at <hi>Belfaſt</hi> for two Nights, and then moved in order to the beſieging of the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Carick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fergus:</hi> on our approach againſt that place the General ſummoned the Town by a Drum, and a Parley was agreed to, but the beſieged inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon very great Conditions, <hi>viz.</hi> to March out with flying Colours, Arms, Baggage, and Plunder, then pretended to be their Property; the General would not agree to them, but in regard there were many Proteſtants in the Town, was willing to comply on reaſonable Terms, but the beſieged utterly refuſed any manner of Conditions, other than what they had propoſed, and if ſuch were not agreed to, would diſpute the Town, which the General his Grace finding them ſo obſtinate, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered 4 Battering Guns, and 2 Morter Pieces, to be planted at the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon houſe very near the Town, and played for a conſiderable time hotly againſt the Caſtle and Town, while the lines of Circumvallation were flinging up, and then Batteries were raiſed on the lines, but being at too great a diſtance, no great prejudice was done; the General ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Batteries to be at great diſtance, did in Perſon ride within 40 paces of the Walls, and appointed the Ground for a new Battery, and running the line of Circumvallation, ſo that the next day 6 Pieces of Cannon and 2 Morters were drawn up to that Ground; from this Battery the Beſiege were ſo warmly ſaluted with our 6 Cannon, one Morter caſting Shells of 600 <hi>l.</hi> weight, and the other flinging 9 ſmall Shells at once into the Town, with a continued Firing of our ſmall Shot from the Trenches, that they hung up a Flag and begg'd for a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, the beſiegers having made 4 Breaches in their Wall, the General being inclinable to preſerve the Proteſtants in the Town, did hearken to a ſecond Treaty; the Conditions were, that the beſieged ſhould March out with their Arms, and to March no further in a day than the Convoy appointed for them pleaſed; the General had not made any Conditions with them, had it not been on the account of the Proteſtants in the Town, he being affronted on the firſt Parley; for when the Enemy had mounted ſome Guns on their Walls, and put other things into order, which could not poſſibly be done without a forbearance of firing from the Trenches, they barbarouſly fired a warning Piece, and took down their Flag, and began to fire furiouſly after the General, and ſome Officers before they could get fairly off; however his Grace was pleaſed to perfect Articles with the beſieged, and the next day they Marcht out about 400, there being ſeveral killed in the Town, but the Country People who were before plundered by them, came down and took what they ſaw was their own, ſo that in two or three miles March, the Enemy loſt moſt of their Baggage; the General was much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at this uſage to the beſieged, but it was a thing altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be prevented, the Rable falling ſo numerouſly upon them, and taking their own goods where ever they found them; for ſeven days the Army lay againſt the Town conſtantly firing, and 2 Frigots lying before the Caſtle firing Broad-ſide after Broad-ſide ſo mighty ſharply that there was a continued light clear round the Town the whol, Night, and to do the beſieged right, they behaved themſelves verey brave as any Men could do. When the Town and Caſtle were actually in our hands, we found ſeveral hundred Barrels of Beef, Pork, Peaſe, Wheat, Malt, and Oatmeal in the Stores, but very little Ammunition. As we Marcht againſt the Town of <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> the General received Advice that 16 Troops of the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Horſe, and 2 Troops of Dragoons were on their March to join us by Major General <hi>Kirk</hi>'s Orders, which they accordingly did, and at that time they were acceptable enough, there being no Horſe landed out of <hi>England;</hi> the next day Collonel <hi>Coy</hi>'s Regiment of Horſe, Collonel <hi>Leviſon</hi>'s Regiment of Dragoons, and ſeveral Regiments of Foot, landed at the <hi>White-houſe</hi> near <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> and upon our March from the Siege, the Lord <hi>Delamare</hi>'s, and Lord <hi>Devonſhire</hi>'s Regiments of Horſe, and Sir <hi>Tho. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owre</hi>'s Regiment of Foot joined us, ſo that we intirely Marcht to <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> ſave Sir <hi>Hen. Ingoldsby</hi>'s Regiment of Foot left in Gariſon at <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> Major General <hi>Kirk</hi> remaining with his and ſome of <hi>London-Derry</hi> Forces at <hi>Coleraine.</hi> On the 3d. of <hi>Sept.</hi> we Marcht to <hi>Lisburn,</hi> having ſent moſt of our heavy Luggage and Guns by Sea, in order to meet us at <hi>Dundalk</hi> or <hi>Drogheda;</hi> and now there being about 800 of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in the <hi>Glens</hi> near <hi>Glenarme,</hi> in the County of <hi>Antrim,</hi> headed by one <hi>Mac Donnel</hi> Naturalſon to the Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> who very much infeſted that Country. One Captain <hi>Stewart</hi> was ordered to detach a certain number out of Sir <hi>H. Ingoldsby</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſuppreſs theſe Rebels, which was accordingly done, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable prey of Cattle got from them.</p>
            <p>On <hi>September</hi> the 4th, we encamped at <hi>Dromore,</hi> being ſeven Miles from <hi>Lisburn,</hi> and received an account that Major General <hi>Mackay</hi> was landed at <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> with ſome Horſe and Dragoons; but this proved a miſtake: On the 5th we encamped at <hi>Loghbracklan,</hi> and the Enemy being then at <hi>Newry,</hi> in a conſiderable Body, commanded by the Duke of <hi>Berwick;</hi> the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Horſe were ordered for the advance Guards, who diſcovering a great Body of Horſe, thought fit to retreat, believing the Enemy might have purſued, and ſo followed them into our Camp, which was in a readineſs to receive them; but the Enemy imagining ſome ſuch thing, did not at all purſue them, but thought to keep the Paſs at the <hi>Newry.</hi> On our March two Drums belonging to the Lord <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi>'s Regiment were hanged near <hi>Dromore,</hi> having revolted and got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Carickfergus</hi> at the time of the Siege. On the 6th, we encamped at <hi>Newry,</hi> the Enemy having deſerted that Paſs, and burnt the Town, with all the Inhabitants Goods, and flinging a piece of Cannon into the River, and moved to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> 8 Miles from <hi>Newry,</hi> the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Horſe (the Duke's <hi>Tartars,</hi> for ſo they were termed,) ſtill keeping the advance Guard, who marched ſo near the Town of <hi>Dundalk,</hi> that they took a prey of 150 Cows from the Enemy's Quarters in their view, with ſome Sheep, and great quantities of Oatmeal and Butter. We continued our Camp at the <hi>Newry</hi> till the 8th, and the General having advice that the Enemy were marched from <hi>Dundalk,</hi> only leaving ſome few Troops there for a Rear-guard, ordered the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Forces to march forward, and detached 50 Foot out of each Regiment, and 20 out of a Troop, to follow the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Forces towards <hi>Dundalk,</hi> having before ſent a Trumpet to tell them, that if they burned the Town, or deſtroyed any more Towns on their retreat, or deſtroy'd the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants Goods, he would not extend mercy to any that ſhould happen in his power, and that Major General <hi>Macarty,</hi> then Priſoner at <hi>Iniskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> ſhould be executed; this ſo terrified them that they march'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without firing the Town of <hi>Dundalk,</hi> or doing any great harm to the Proteſtants there; and at 8 of the Clock at Night we entered the Town with theſe Detachments, and found there great ſtores of Wheat and other Grain, and Salt, laid up in ſtores for the Iriſh Army; when the whole Body of the Army had moved up, we encamped at <hi>Dundalk,</hi> the one part of the Army on the <hi>Newry</hi> ſide of the River, and the Dutch Regiments, with the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Forces on <hi>Dundalk</hi> ſide, and in ſome few days after had marched forward, but that our Cannon and Proviſions did not come by Sea ſo ſoon as was expected, nor were there draught-horſes for our March in caſe both Ammunition, Guns, and Proviſion had come by the time expected; which was the chief cauſe of the Army not moving upwards towards <hi>Dublin,</hi> Comiſſary <hi>Shales</hi> not ſending the Horſes over in due time: Upon our coming to <hi>Dundalk</hi> the Army plentifully fed on the Lord of <hi>Duleek</hi>'s Mutton, he having fled, and in command with the Rebels: Upon our approach to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> the Enemy likewiſe deſerted <hi>Atherdee</hi> being 8 Miles from <hi>Drogheda,</hi> and ſome of the Engliſh Forces advanced ſo far, and then the late King <hi>James</hi> deſigned to rendezvouze his Forces, and encamp on the other ſide of the River of <hi>Boyn</hi> beyond <hi>Drogheda;</hi> but finding the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Army did not move forward, ſent a Body of Horſe and ſome Foot to <hi>Atherdee,</hi> and ſecured that Town, baniſhing the Proteſtants and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Subſtance; between which place and <hi>Dundalk</hi> there was ſome ſmall skirmiſhing, and particularly at <hi>Mapestown-bridge</hi> our Scou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s met ſome of the Enemy, killed about 9, and took ſome Priſoners; in which action one of the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Horſe and an Engliſh Dragoon fell by an Ambuſcado. On the 15th, the Enemy's Van guard, conſiſting of 4000 Horſe were ſeen to advance within 4 or 5 Miles of our Cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and
<pb facs="tcp:36060:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>the General not having Horſe enough to engage them, ordered ſome Trenches to be caſt up a ſmall way beyond the Town of <hi>Dundalk,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and the Enemy, where the two Dutch Regiments were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly encamped, and 2 Regiments mounted the Trenches every day, and ordered 8 pieces of Cannon to be planted upon the Works. On the 16th Major General <hi>Scragmore</hi> embarked for <hi>England;</hi> and on the 17th, Mr. <hi>Holſort,</hi> the General's Secretary, died at <hi>Dundalk:</hi> On the 18th, 100 Men out of each Regiment were detached to bring the Forage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Enemy and us: On the ſame day 24 Companies of Foot and 4 Troops of the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Forces joyned us in the Camp, and brought 600 Cows with them, leaving one Regiment of Foot, and ſome Troops of Horſe at <hi>Iniskilling.</hi> About this time Collonel <hi>Guſtavus Hamilton</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of Foot, Collonel <hi>Langſton</hi>'s Horſe, and part of Collonel <hi>Villers</hi>'s Regiment of Horſe, landed at <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> which Horſe were daily expected in the Camp; but Collonel <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Foot were ordered to <hi>Carickfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> and Sir <hi>Hen. Ingoldsby</hi>'s to march to the Camp. In this time the Enemy daily encreaſed, and came downwards in great Bodies; and on the 19th, the Iriſh Scouts appeared within a Mile of the Town of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalk,</hi> with whom out Out-guards had a ſmart Diſpute, in which ſome fell on both ſides. On the 20th, two Gentlemen came from the Iriſh Army, and gave the General an account that the Iriſh were very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, but many of them Rabble, and that ſeveral Proteſtants had great deſire to come off if they could doe it with ſafety; and that the Late King <hi>James</hi> was in perſon at the head of them, and were encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at <hi>Lurgan Race,</hi> 3 Miles from <hi>Dundalk.</hi> On the 21ſt, about 7 of the Clock in the Morning ſeveral of the Enemy's Troops were ſeen ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing near our Camp, and about 10 the whole Body of Horſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of 10000, drew up into 5 diviſions within half a Mile of our Trenches, their whole Body of Foot being about 35000 were in the Rear of the Horſe; which account the General had from a Deſerter, who farther ſaid, that although they appeared in ſo great numbers, yet they had not above 4 or 5000 good Horſe, the reſt being ill mounted, and worſe armed, ſeveral of their Horſe being Lanciers for want of other Arms, and the greateſt part of the Foot a perfect Rabble, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for plunder than doing ſervice: Some of the Enemy's Horſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced within Musket Shot of our Trenches, but were forced to retreat, being warmly received by ſome Granadeers at the Bog ſide, between our Camp and the Enemy's Body, and thereupon the General ordered a good guard of Horſe to march towards them, but the Bog being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, no action happened: His Grace likewiſe ordered 300 of the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Foot, commanded by Collonel <hi>Tiffin,</hi> to march down to the Bog ſide, the Enemy having drawn down a Body of Foot to the other ſide of the Bog, and lined all the Hedges and Ditches thereabouts; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral firings were on both ſides, but being at too great a diſtance, no great harm was done; and ſo brave was the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Foot, that they paſſionately deſired to march over the Bog, and in order to it, every Man of them ſtript off his Coat, ſo that inſtead of a grey Regiment they appeared in white, being their uſual way in fighting to enable them for better action in the ſervice; the General with a ſtrong Guard rid round the Bog, and poſted Men at all places where he apprehended danger; in this manner both Armies ſtood in readineſs, but no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and after the late King <hi>James</hi> with his whole Army, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſo for 4 or 5 hours, he marched back to his Camp. On the 23d, 6 Men were taken, one whereof being an experienced Soldier, but a private Centinel, had drawn a Scheme of our Camp, where we lay open, how the Enemy might have fallen in upon us, how our Men ſickned, what number of Horſe and Foot we were, and how victualled, and was going over to the Late King, but he and the other 5 were taken, and this Scheme found upon him; ſo that they were all hanged, and 150 more of the French who were ſuſpected, ſent Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to <hi>Cheſter.</hi> It is believed that the Late King had ſome aſſurance of the French Regiments deſerting, if both Armies had then engaged. On the 25th, we had advice from <hi>Sligo,</hi> that Collonel <hi>Lloyd,</hi> with 5 Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Foot, and 4 Troops of Horſe and Dragroons, had engaged the Enemy at <hi>Abbyboyle,</hi> and killed 300 in the Church, and in the purſuit took Collonel <hi>Kelly,</hi> Collonel <hi>Dillon,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Farrel,</hi> and killed 300 more, having the purſuit of them for about 11 or 12 Miles, and had their Horſe been firſt, might have cut off the whole Body, being 5000; in which action but 6 of the Proteſtants were killed, and 5 wounded; for joy of which great Conqueſt, there was a running Fire through the Camp, and the Guns in the Fleet returned the ſame.</p>
            <p>On the 6th of <hi>Octob.</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army decamped and Marcht towards <hi>Drogheda,</hi> having firſt burned the whole Country about them, ſetting all their Huts on fire before they marcht away: Salt, Tobacco, and Brandy were very ſcarce among them, and more eſpecially Salt, for that the Soldiers were forced to boil their Meat in Salt Water, little or no Silver was current amongſt them, but all Copper. On the 6th. the General had an account how Collonel <hi>Lloyd</hi> had taken <hi>James</hi> Town and <hi>Carugdrumroosk</hi> from the Enemy; on the 8th. 150 Horſe Granadeers, 150 Dragroons, and 150 <hi>Inskilling</hi> Horſe were detacht to March to <hi>Sligo,</hi> commanded by Collonel <hi>Ruſſel</hi> and Collonel <hi>Tiffin:</hi> At their coming to <hi>Sligo</hi> the Enemy were prepared for them, and a ſmart Engagement happened; but at length about 80 of the Granadeers poſſeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the Fort, and very well defended the ſame for ſome days a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Collonel <hi>Sarsfield</hi> and his Forces; but being ſtraightened for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, were forced to capitulate and made honourable Conditions, which were performed by Collonel <hi>Sarsfield,</hi> yet he endeavoured by all fair means to bring theſe Men over to King <hi>James</hi> upon promiſes of Preferments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they utterly refuſed him. When the late King had decamed, his Grace the Duke of <hi>Schonberg</hi> ordered the greateſt part of the Army to Winter Quarters, making <hi>Lisburn</hi> his own head Quarters; but there being ſome Shipping in the River of <hi>Dundalk,</hi> which could not ſail for want of a Wind, Collonel <hi>L. Moleniere</hi> was left Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our at <hi>Dundalk,</hi> with 4 Regiments of Foot, and ſome Horſe, to preſerve theſe Shipping from the Enemy until they could get out, and then the 4 Regiments marcht intirely from <hi>Dundalk</hi> to Winter Quarters; Sir <hi>H. Ingoldsby</hi>'s Regiment being left at the <hi>Newry</hi> the frontier Gariſon. As ſoon as the Proteſtant Forces had Marcht from <hi>Dundalk,</hi> the Enemy poſſeſſed themſelves of that place, and moſt of the Creates, or poor Country People, droven up by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, returned to that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and remained upon the Mountains between <hi>Dundalk</hi> and the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſeveral of them endeavouring to bring what ſmall ſtock of Cattle they had into the County of <hi>Down;</hi> ſuch as brought any goods with them were admitted to go into the Counties of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim,</hi> but ſuch as brought nothing, were ſent back to the Mountains again, and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to go into our Country. Sir <hi>Hen. Ingoldsby</hi>'s Regiment being at the <hi>Newry,</hi> commanded by Leiutenant Collonel <hi>Purcel,</hi> Governour of that place, remained peaceably there till about the 5th. or 6th. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> at which time the Governour had an Account of a conſiderable Body, both Horſe and Foot, of the Enemy were marching towards <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and intended to attack the Gariſon at <hi>Newry,</hi> being the Key of the <hi>North;</hi> whereupon 60 Men and a Captain were paſſed at Narrow Water, 12 with a Serjeant at <hi>Fatham</hi> Caſtle, being a paſs on the River, which was fordable when the Tide was out; and likewiſe a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable number of Men were at Pointz paſs, and theſe being the only dangerous Paſſes and thus fortified, Collonel <hi>Purcel</hi> thought himſelf ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure as to the Paſs at the <hi>Newry;</hi> but about the 8th. or 9th of <hi>December</hi> 1700 Foot, and 6 Troops of Horſe and Dragoons, came within a quarter of a mile of <hi>Newry,</hi> out of which 300 were detacht and ſent into the Town by break of day, having killed our out Guards: Upon which the Gariſon received the Allarm, yet ſo very quick was the Enemy, that they were in the Town before the main Guard could draw out, there not being above 40 effectual Men, who behaved themſelves ſo well, that they forced that part of the Enemy marching up from the Bridge to retreat, but ſome of the Enemy getting ſooner into the Town, and having notice where the Officers quartered, killed Captain <hi>Whitfield</hi> going out of his Quarters, and killed Captain <hi>Miller</hi> in the ſtreet; Leiutenant <hi>Shrould</hi> received a wound on the thigh, whereof he died, and 4 of the Soldiers killed. There was killed of the Enemy a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel, with 14 Men in the Town, beſides ſeveral taken off dead, and many wounded, of which the Governour had a certain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count afterwards: The main Body finding the forlorn thus defeated, marcht back to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and altho' they have often reſolved to attack the Gariſon again, have never yet attempted it; and ſince they could not come into the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> at the Paſſes of Naview Water, fathom Caſtle, Newry or Pointz his Paſs, they intended to attack the Gariſon at <hi>Belturbet</hi> in the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> then and now under the command of Collonel <hi>Wolſely,</hi> Collonel of a Regiment of the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Horſe, and think to get into the <hi>North</hi> that way; but Collonel <hi>Wolſely</hi> having an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their deſign reſolved to prevent them, and on the 12th. of <hi>March</hi> with 700 Foot and 300 Horſe marcht towards <hi>Cavan,</hi> where 2000 of the Enemy were; his purpoſe was to fall upon them by break of day, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but 7 Miles to March from <hi>Belturbet</hi> to <hi>Cavan;</hi> but the Enemy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving poſted ſome ſmall number of Men at a place called <hi>Butlers</hi>-Bridge, the Collonel could not paſs there without allarming them, which would very ſoon after be at <hi>Cavan,</hi> therefore it was agreed to March peaceably up the River-ſide, to afoord at a place called <hi>Bullynacarrig</hi> being 4 Miles out of the way, when the Collonel had advanced as far as this place, the Enemy had likewiſe ſome Men poſted there, who gave notice to them of <hi>Cavan,</hi> the Collonel notwithſtanding marcht all his Men over the Biver, and ſoon after day-light was within half a mile of <hi>Cavan</hi> on <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> ſide of the Town, but inſtead of ſurprizing them, he found their Gariſon re-inforced by 2000, and the whole Body fairly formed into a defenſive poſture, and ready to receive him, commanded by the Duke of <hi>Berwick;</hi> this much ſurprized him, and to retreat would certainly ruin the whole buſineſs, therefore the Collonel detached 150, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted them at a convenient paſs for a reſerve, and with the remainder charged the Enemy; the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Dragoons made the firſt on-ſet, but were forced to loſe ground, upon this the Collonel commanded ſome <hi>Dutch</hi> Granadeers to march up, who behaved themſelves ſo well, that the Enemy loſt ground; by which means the <hi>Iniskilling</hi> Dragoons rallied and joined the body again, and then for an hour the matter was horly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, and at length the Enemy took to flight, one part of them made to the Fort, and the other towards <hi>Finah.</hi> In the purſuit were killed 139 beſides ſeveral Officers, Collonel, <hi>Edmond O Reily,</hi> with ſome other Officers of great Note was killed in the firſt Engagement; on our ſide we loſt 4 Captains and 20 Men. When this action was over, the <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilling</hi> Men began to plunder the Town, and were ſtragling in odd numbers about the place, which the Enemy diſcovering from the Fort, drew out a freſh party, and came down upon them; but the reſerve as I mentioned before, being in order and a readineſs engaged them, and forced them into the Fort again, and then Collonel <hi>Wolſley</hi> ordered the Town to be burned, and likewiſe burned <hi>Killiſhandrew</hi> on his March to <hi>Belturbet;</hi> in ſome few days after, a party of Horſe fell on ſome of the Enemy, who were intrencht at <hi>Butlers</hi>-Bridge, killing about 36 and taking ſeveral Priſoners, with the chief Officers commanding there, in which ſecond action not a man of the Proteſtants were loſt. As for the Gariſon of <hi>Charlemont,</hi> they are in a manner blockt up, for ſince Collonel <hi>Withers</hi> burned the Bridge, and took their Boats, they cannot make any incurſions into the Country, we having Gariſons at <hi>Dungannon, Armagh, Benburl,</hi> and <hi>Loghgall;</hi> the General took a view of the place and makes no doubt of having it before the Army take the Field, yet the Enemy have not been idle in fortifying this place, for they have flung up a Ditch on the out-ſide of the Trench, equally high with the Wall, ſo that although the Caſtle be of it ſelf weak, yet the Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations about it are ſtrong. The Prince of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi> is arrived with the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Forces at <hi>Carickfergus,</hi> whither his Grace the Duke of <hi>Schon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> is juſt now a going to ſee them, the <hi>Mary</hi> Yatcht has brought to <hi>Belfaſt</hi> a Boat that was going with eight Paſſengers from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin.</hi> The Army is now in a very good Condition, both as to Health, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and well provided with Proviſins, and are moſt impatient for the Seaſon of the Year in taking the Field.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Partridge</hi> at the Poſt-Houſe at <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
